Guide to the Angel Hair Archive 1965-1973 MSS 4 MSS.004
Fales Library and Special Collections
Angel Hair Archive
1965-1973
Fales Library and Special Collections
Angel Hair Books (New York, N.Y.)
MSS.004
3.75 Linear Feet in 7 manuscript boxes and 1 half manuscript box.
Angel Hair was a small avant-garde poetry magazine. The Angel Hair Archive is a collection of correspondence written to the editors, Anne Waldman and Lewis Warsh, and includes manuscripts, and issues of Angel Hair.
Provenance
The Angel Hair Archive was purchased from Serendipity Books in March 1972.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open without restrictions. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Historical/Biographical Note:
Angel Hair magazine and publishing was led by poets and writers, Anne Waldman and Lewis Warsh from the mid-1960's through the mid-1970's. Anne Waldman has published over thirty books and pamphlets of poetry, including: 'Fast Speaking Woman,' 'Helping the Dreamer: New & Selected Poems,' and 'Makeup on Empty Space.' Coincident with her work on Angel Hair, She was Director of the Poetry Project at St. Marks Church, and together with Allen Ginsberg, co-founded the Jack Kerouac School of Disembodied Poetics at Naropa University in Boulder, Colorado, where she still teaches writing. Lewis Warsh has published two novels: 'Agnes & Sally' and 'A Free Man,' short stories, and numerous books of poetry. He also co-founded United Artists Books. Angel Hair was first run from their apartment on St. Marks Place in Manhattan where Waldman and Warsh mixed with many literati as well as artists and musicians of the time. Contributors to the magazine included a wide range of poets: Clark Coolidge, Alice Notley, Hannah Weiner, Tom Clark, Bernadette Mayer, Kenward Elmslie, Robert Creeley, Joanne Kyger, Ted Greenwald, Lorenzo Thomas, John Wieners, Joe Brainard, Ron Padgett among many others. Eventually Angel Hair left New York and began publishing books, and Warsh and Waldman amicably went their separate ways. In its years of operation, Angel Hair was a very long-lived and influential publisher on the small press scene. An anthology: 'Angel Hair Sleeps with a Boy in my Head: The Angel Hair Anthology' was published by Granary books (2001).
Sources:
'Angel Hair Sleeps with a Boy in my Head: the Angel Hair Anthology' [summary]. New York: Granary Books, 29 Sept. 2002 [http://www.granarybooks.com/books/angel_hair/angel_hair1.html].
Waldman, Anne. 'Angel Hair feature: Introduction'. Jacket-6, 4 Dec. 2002. 7 Jan. 2003 [http://jacketmagazine.com/16/ah1-wald.html].
Scope and Content Note
The Angel Hair Archive is a collection of correspondence submitted to its editors, Anne Waldman and Lewis Warsh, from 1965 to 1973. The collection includes manuscripts, issues 1-6 of Angel Hair, and original manuscripts of 'Bun.' Collection highlights include letters written by Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Jasper Johns, Paul Blackburn, Robert Bly, Sam Shepard, Gerard Malanga, John Giorno, Allen Ginsberg, and Richard Brautigan.
SERIES DESCRIPTION
Series I: Correspondence: contains 6 boxes of correspondence to the editors, Anne Waldman and Lewis Warsh. Noted correspondents include: Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Jasper Johns, Paul Blackburn, Robert Bly, Sam Shepard, Gerard Malanga, John Giorno, Allen Ginsberg, and Richard Brautigan. Included in series I (box 1, folder 1) is the 'Archive List' which includes descriptions of each item in the collection but also a brief bio of each writer in the collection.
Series II: Production files: contains 1 box of production files, including catalogues, a galley proof, manuscripts, mockups and issues 1-6 of Angel Hair, and original manuscripts of Bun.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by subject/author and then chronologically.
The files are grouped into two series.
Missing Title
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Productions Files and Publications
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
Correspondence.; Galley proofs.; Little magazines.; Magazines (Periodicals); New York (N.Y.).; American poetry -- 20th century.; New York (N.Y.) -- Intellectual life -- 20th century.; American fiction -- 20th century.; Literature, Experimental.; Avant-garde (Aesthetics); Small presses -- New York (State) -- New York.; Authors, American -- 20th century.; Poets, American -- 20th century.; Scripts (documents); Manuscripts for publication.; Johns, Jasper, 1930-; Warsh, Lewis; Malanga, Gerard; Shepard, Sam, 1943-2017; Waldman, Anne, 1945-; Bly, Robert; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997; Brautigan, Richard; Giorno, John; Ferlinghetti, Lawrence; Blackburn, Paul
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Correspondence: Archive List, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Archive Purchase from Serendipity Books, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Abbott, Keith Abrams, Sam Adam, Helen, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Allen, Donald Amram, David Anderson, Terry, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Anderson, Jack Ardery, Peter Plimpton, Jack Ashbery, John, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Awards and Grants, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Bathurst, Bill Belies, Sinclair Benedikt, Michael, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Benjamin, Jerry Bergé, Carol, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Berkson, William, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Berkson, William, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Berkson, William, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Berkson, William, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Berkson, William, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Berkson, William, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Berrigan, Ted, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Blackburn, Paul Bland, Peter Bly, Robert, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Bookstores, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Borregard, Ebbe, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: Brainard, Joe, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Brainard, Joe, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Brautigan, Richard, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Brodey, Jim, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Manuscript: Brodey, Jim, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Brownstein, Michael Bunage, Katherine Burckhardt, Rudy, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Business Contracts, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Carey, Steve Carroll, James Carroll, Paul, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Catheart, Adrian Ceravolo, Joseph Cerf, Christopher, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Charters, Samuel Chiarello, Gail, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Clark, Tom, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Clark, Tom, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Clark, Tom, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Clarke, Jack Codrescu, Andrei Cohen, Robert, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Cohen, Scott Coleman, Victor Collom, Jack, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Coolidge, Clark, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Manuscript: Coolidge, Clark, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Cott, Jonathan, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Crabtree, Lee Creeley, Robert Crozier, Andrew, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Dawson, Fielding Delany, Chip Dine, Jim, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: DiPalma, Raymond DiPrima, Diane Disch, Tom, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Dorn, Edward Doss, Margot Duhamel, Vaughn, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Duncan, Robert Elmslie, Kenward Ellingham, Lewis, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Eshleman, Clayton, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Fagin, Larry, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Ferlinghetti, Lawrence Ferrari, Mary Ford, Charles Henri, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Franks, David Gallup, Dick Gilfillan, Merrill, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Ginsberg, Allen Ginsberg, Louis Giorno, John, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Gluck, Louise Godfrey, John Golde, Morris, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Gotterman, Leslie Gottlieb, Annie Gray, Darrell, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Greene, Jonathan Greenwald, Ted Groffsky, Maxine, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Grossinger, Richard Guest, Barbara Guston, Philip, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Hall, Donald Harris, Robert, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Harwood, Lee, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Harwood, Lee, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: Henderson, David Higgins, Richard Hine, Daryl, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence: Holden, Steven Hollo, Anselm Horowitz, Michael, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence: Howell, Robert, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence: Hoyen, Andrew, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence: Jeanclos, Katherine Johns, Jasper Katz, Alex, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Katz, Leonardo Kimball, George Kissam, Edward, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Koch, Kenneth Koch, Steven Koller, James, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Kostelanetz, Richard Krauss, Ruth Kuzma, Greg, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Kyger, Joanne, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: LeSueur, Joe Loewinson, Ronald Lowell, Mrs. Robert, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: MacAdams, Lewis MacBeth, George MacLow, Jackson, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: McClure, Michael MacNaughton, Duncan MacSweeny, Barry, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Mailing Lists, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Malanga, Gerard, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Malanga, Gerard, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Manglesdorf, Richard Mariah, Paul Marshall, Jack Matthews, Harry, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Mayer, Bernadette, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Meltzer, David Merwin, W.S. Moberg, David, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Mottram, Eric Murphy, Rosalie Murray, Catherine, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Nemerov, Howard Nolan, Patrick North, Charles Notley, Alice, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Obenzinger, Hilton O'Gallagher, Liam Owen, Maureen, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Padgett, Ron, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: Perreault, John Pinelli, Joseph Plymell, Charles, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence: Poetry Readings, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence: Presson, William Pritchett, Henry Prynne, Jeremy, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence: Rago, Henry Randall, Margaret Raworth, Thomas Reznikoff, Charles, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Ricard, René, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Riley, Peter Rorem, Ned, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Rosenberg, David, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Rosenberg, David, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Rosenberg, David, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Rosenberg, David, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Sallis, James Saroyan, Aram Schaff, David, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Schiff, Harris, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Schjeldahl, Peter, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Schneeman, George Schuyler, James Shepherd, Sam, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Silver, James Silverton, Michael Sinclair, David, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Sladeck, John Slomen, Joel Smith, Patti, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Stanley, George Stanton, Johnny Stein, Charles, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Strand, Mark Thomas, Lorenzo Thomas, William Thormann, Janet Thorpe, John, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Torregian, Sotere, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Towle, Tony Tysh, George Van Newkirk, Allen Vega, Janine, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Veitch, Tom, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Wade, Stephen Wakoski, Diane, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Waldman, Anne, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Warsh, Lewis, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Weishaus, Joel Whalen, Philip Wieners, John, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Wilentz, Theodore Williams, Calen Winkfield, Trevor, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Series II: Production files and Publications
  - Catalogues [#1, #2, #3, #8], undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Galley Proof: 'Three Madrigals' John Ashbery, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Manuscript: Issue #1, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Manuscript: Issue #2, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Manuscript: Issue #3, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Manuscript: Issue #4, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Manuscript: Issue #5, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Manuscript: Issue #6, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Mockup: Issue #3, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Mockup: Issue #5, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Issue #1, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Issue #2, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Issue #3, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Issue #4, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Issue #5, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Issue #6, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Original mss. Of Bun ( Angel Hair, 1968) by Tom Clark and Ron Padgett, cover by Jim Dine., undated (Box 8, Folder 1)